hello welcome
back now we have the much anticipated
student presentation that your adviser
Alex recently told us will be awesome by
Viet dong win on Dynamic prior
preference learning for scalable robust
deep active inference so thank you V
take it
away hello uh hello hello everyone um my
name is zet I'm from uh the neuro adap
Computing Laboratory um Department in
computer science seest technology um and
I am uh Alex advis uh and today I'll be
talking about Dynamic PR preference
learning to scale Aus active
INF so yeah first of all want to talk
about the motivation for this so
nowadays you know from fure work in
robotics um excels in implementing
robots behavior and planning for example
um creating um we can you know creating
autonomous robots that can actively
explore in the envir
um additionally um acquiring we can also
do a lot of Robotics applications for
example acquiring knowledge and learn
skills continuously um and um this also
envisioned um cognitive and
developmental robotics um so there just
a goal um for um robots robotics
research um that's we can try to build a
robots that can continuously develop
through interactions with the
environment and their learning processes
um and it is also also better um to have
interactions with their uh physical and
social world in the manner of human
learning and cognitive development so
there's a lot of Robotics applications
um around um and for example one
application can be to build ASA robots
and um building um social collaborative
robots and stuff like that um so
underlying um all these robot work um uh
we it's like active inference research
where we um often build a generative
models
um um it's so the development of
Robotics actually depends a lot on activ
framework because um there's a great
need for research um that integrates the
generative World model into robotics
control system um as also deep learning
is increasingly used in constructing
complex action planning algorithms for
solving control tasks
um so um we can see that there's a need
for scaling um active in system
especially and deep active INF system um
to integrate into the real world
applications so um resar in active INF
has led to many improvements um in terms
of robustness of um model based agents
that applies to both M processes um and
partially absorbable MVPs or P
MVPs so an example of an mdp environment
should be Mountain car um uh for those
who um knows or studies reinforcement
learning already and um this m carment
environments um in mdp we only know POS
velocity right um and that is the actual
state of the environment um but when we
get to PVP for example like robotic
tasks um we as agents see only the image
frame and we do not know the under lying
states such as position and orientation
of the block or um join state of the
robots for example right um so basically
active inference is basically a form of
inference and learning that sticks to
balance first of all the um goal
orienting objectives or PRI preference
um so this signal exploit um the
instrumental signal um so that the
agents can seek the goal um and try to
pursue its goal um and the other thing
it needs to balance the epistemic terms
or epistemic signal where the foraging
uh it's cares about foraging and
exploration driving signals um so
researcher often actually encounter
great difficulty in providing the agent
with effective prior preference as well
as Computing useful instrumental signal
from the agents the priors um especially
in the real world applications where um
the environment is very complex the
robotic control task and um the
trajectory or partway um to be desirable
um and Tas specific goals um often
requires uh a very very long um
trajectory of preference um so it is not
that ABS practical to provide uh a prior
preference distributions especially the
um stream or roll out of go
images so that is the reason why we need
to find a way to also learn to generate
the prior preference signal in active
inference so on the right here is just
our Umar preliminary results um but
we'll get to that in a
moment so
um yes so we actually uh given without
uh all of this uh right we need to
um uh we need to predict a u uh drawout
trajectory of a goal um States
dynamically right um it can be a goal
state or goal observations but basically
the goal is um if you look on the figure
on top here um the top row is the real
trajectory where you see the mountain
car right there's a car that it needs to
go backward and to build some kind of a
momentum and then go full to the right
to get to the um to the flag if it is
only going to the right and it can it
does not have the enough momentum to to
go to to the top of the hill so um so in
here uh is the um actual observations
you can see that the trajectory is um a
successful trajectory and the goal here
is to um for each uh observation at each
time step we predict a um immediate
predict predicted PR preference um image
or goal at that single time step so that
we have um the instrumental signal or
idea of uh what we are trying to learn
and then um from that we learn the
actions planning uh on uh from the PRI
preference
signal so in this talk we are we
specifically analyze this issue um the
issue of um uh prior preference learning
um in the current literature um and
discuss potential resolutions for
scaling the instrumental signal
inherence to active inflence by
introducing the um contrasted recurrent
State prior preference or
crsb um this is the model um learning
framework that um we also have um done
in the past so uh this methodology
frames active inference agents in term
of progressively constructing and adapt
adapting um a prior preference um at
each time step so this also facilitate
the Dynamics emission of a useful or
dense very dense um instrumental signal
uh at each time step so we also um study
how our prior preference adaptation
scheme um when operating jointly with
the Laten space driven epistemic
foraging terms uh offers active inflence
agent um a very nice U flexibility in
challenging problem con context um such
as um spars to reward um environments um
and also composed of uh continuous
observation and action space right
example um for example robotic task um
they only we often like do not know the
spars um do not know the dense reward um
functions in the actual real
environments and we we only know if the
robot has risked the goal or not right
um and also all these environments has
you know varying goal States so um we
can also see that providing the uh uh or
manually craft the uh distributions of
goal is very not very um
practical so uh yeah so here here's the
outline of this talk on the introduction
I've had just covered um so we so first
of all I'll just assume that's uh
everyone is new to active inference and
I'm just going to briefly cover active
inference backgrounds and deep active
inference um and also cover a little bit
about um prior PRI preference learning
and problems um
uh of all those prior preference
learning framework and then I'm just
going now go through the actual
methodology which is the dynamic Prime
preference learning um and then first of
all is the world model um next is the
self-revision mechanism and then next is
the um learning Prime preference models
and then finally um putting all them
together um to make an agent um and then
um I'll show the results and then
discussion
okay so first of all um I want to um
cover a little bit about active
inference um so just a brief overview
about how active inference work and what
is the underlying theories behind it um
so um it is a ma mathematical framework
that describes how intelligent systems
are human interact with the environment
um so it describe it also describe the
environment as the generative process um
and the intelligent systems um are the
agent or um us as generative model um so
active INF is built on top of the free
energy principles um this means that we
as agent or intelligent system
continuously observe the environment and
forming our and correcting our belief or
our own representation of the
world um so the generative process um
defines a real world environment here
right um this is treated as the data
Generation Um process where the
information patterns are sensed by the
agent so you can see that's the um
hidden State underlying hidden States
denoted as here um it's generate a sense
of um some kind of um a observations um
denoted o and this is also um sensed by
um our in intelligence
system so on the right here is the
generative model uh is uh the actual
agent that we are trying to build on the
intelligent system right um the
intelligence system also has an internal
State um which is trying to um estimate
the generative process um States um so
this is called um the prior or the
internal relief prior to the
observations of the environment at a
particular time stamp so this is denoted
as the random variable s or state and P
of s here um is the distribution over
the random variable s um so this make
the agent's generative model um the
generative model represents the agent's
approximation of this generative process
um in this world um by continuously
seeing the observations or making the
observation oh um and modified or
updating uh its belief so we actually
call the belief um s after uh being
updated after uh making the observation
or the posterior because it is the
posterior after um making the
observation
right so in order to learn the model and
estimates the posterior we first need to
in introduce these terms um first of all
is the prior over State um which is
denoted as PS which is also the
distribution over state right um P ofo
here is the model evidence um it is the
distribution over the current
observations um denoting how well is our
model at predicting the real data um and
in order to compute this easily this is
often written at the sum of probability
uh
of observation given every single
state and then next one is p of O given
s this is the likelihoods um and the
probability uh this is the probability
of an observation given a state so this
is a function it gives a probability
given an input States and then the the
last one is the posterior functions uh p
as given o which is um the posterior
function that Maps the observation to
the states um so uh normally in
traditional active inference um the
peror function would be uh the the
transpose of the likelihood Matrix for
example um and deep learning literature
um it is often called a encoder and the
likelihood here is a
decoder so how do we estimate the postor
now um we have to find
belief that maximize the modal evidence
right because um at the current time
points uh there there is only one single
observation o here and it is real right
so P of o p of that observation um it's
going to be uh one right so it should be
the probability of
one um and then um we use the state to
estimate um the observations and then it
has to be the uh the probability of one
two right so uh that arrives us at the
conclusion that we have to um maximize
the model evidence
PFO so maximizing P of O is also
minimizing equal to minimizing minus l p
of O right because um it is uh
minimizing the surprise um
so in the beginning we say that we
continuously update our belief after
making an an observations of the
environment um we call the belief after
making an observation a posterior um
this is Q of s
right um so to compute posterior we want
to put in a um we just want to um call
this you know any kind of um
distributions um over States um then for
example we can sample it we can
randomize it right um and then we try to
gradually trick this distribution so
that it's used the highest modal
evidence or it's used the lowest
surprise so how do we choose U the
actual uh posterior um so that it bus
the lowest surprise right so in minus l
p of O here is the actual um uh
minimizing surprise that objective that
we are wanting to to minimize right so
we can uh analyze it like uh we can uh
do it with a base theorem this not Bas
theorem but base formula or theories
yeah um and then
uh to evaluate the surprise minus log P
of O we need to sum out um the hidden
variable s from The Joint distribution
POS um
but well this summations there's a
problem right because that we do not
know like all the hidden States all the
hidden variables in the environments um
it is hidden from us right so it is
normally very very hard to uh to sum up
all these um State values so uh if we
cannot sum it up then we can try to
approximate it
so first we introduce a posterior um in
into this uh sum right we multiply both
the denominator and the numerator by the
posterior um so this is the belief that
we are trying to tweak right so um in
here we're trying to um took this
posterior so that um we can um minimize
this
term so this gives us a r sum where s uh
the ratio um P oos and um over the the
distributions um Q of s is weed by the Q
of s this is like weed sum
right so according to the inequality of
convexity or gen inequality says that's
the convex function of a weighted means
is always smaller um than the weed means
of the same convex function um so you
can see
the convex function here is minus lock
of something right
so minus lock of something is just a
hyper uh is just a parabol something
like here um and uh this is smaller than
a what means of the complex functions
also we put this some outside right um
so this is also applied to the context
of probability
Theory um and then we can arrive at this
uh yeah this
equations so formally it's called an
upper bounds uh this one right a
quantity that approach from the above
right so this is also means that this is
a free energy um when we find a
posterior that minimize this free energy
term we will have a chance of
approaching the lower surprise points um
which potentially increasing the uh
modor evidence
so after we have this terms right here
we can just uh put the minus inside and
then it's become this form this is the
conventional form that we call variation
of re energy um and after decomposing
this we will have these two form uh
which is the K Divergence of between the
posterior and the prior uh minus the
weighted sum uh of the lock of of um the
uh um P of or given s which is the
posterior
functions or no this is
likelihood so basically um the K
Divergence term is called the complexity
and the minus l p of our given s is
called accuracy term where the
complexity terms comput how um supplies
are State um to State distributions
posterior and the prior are far away
from each other or not right and the
accuracy terms uh defines how accurate
our model is predicting um the actual
observations right so this is also
relatable to the variational auto
encoder where um we comput the loss of
the variation Auto encod um to be the K
Divergence of the posterior and the Gin
distribution with a mean of zero and a
standard deviation of one and then we
also have the uh mean Square arrows of
the actual predictions of the images
right um and then VIP and MF is a little
bit um different than from variation of
out coder VP is variation of free energy
and mfp is marginal free energy as in
the um active inference tutorial um the
paper U so marginal free energy says
that um we compute the CH Divergence
between the poster and the prior and the
prior here is computed from the
transition model um not the um not the
normal distributions of mean of zero and
this standard equation of
one so uh here is the uh General model
of trying to build a deactive inference
model right so here's first of all we're
trying to encode right using the
posterior functions so in active
inference this is the p s given o is the
transpose of the likelihood Matrix P of
given s this is normally learns with the
cical distributions and using the orally
conjugate
prior um and then uh in the Deep
learning literature um this is often
known as the encoder U that's uh Often
parameterized by the neuron Network um
and then o here is often be an image and
state here is just um some
hidden vectors that we are trying to
compute and then next one is the um La
function right so normally we text in
the states um of um the agent and then
we're trying to estimate the uh
predictions the observation predictions
right um so in traditional active INF
this is known as the likelihood Matrix
or likelihoods um per se um this is also
learns with the Cal categorical
distribution and using the conjugate
prior and deep learning literature um
this is known often known as the decoder
um that is often parameterized by a Neo
Network so uh as we know the variation
of free energy formula the complexity
terms K Divergence here right
and the um uh accuracy term is the minus
l p right given s um so here we compute
the K Divergence between the encode
States and the actual prior States here
and then um next one we comput the um
actual L probability of the predicted
observations and the actual observations
right here
um and that makes the um whole
objectives where we compute the two uh
objectives right here that's uh also be
the um variation of free energy
formula so we just talk about how
inference um inactive instrument work
but there's more we want to build an
inference system that can interact with
the world right so when it comes to
interaction between the agent and and
the environment we also need to have
action
and um also roll out in time step right
so basically we have another elements
here which is at and remember I also
mentioned the transition model right so
after we take an action in the world um
we um the the world um or the
environments evaluates one step right
and it uh it change its own State and
then emits a new observations um and
with we as agents or intelligence system
also try to predict um given the action
in the current states what is the next
States and what and this States is the
prior over um the states of the next
town step where we have not made the
observation OT plus1 yet so after we
have the St plus1 as prior um we do the
same process as I have mentioned before
so uh we make up observations um try to
change um our belief uh after making
that observations and then learns from
the uh new observations to take our
prior into the
posterior so here we learn it um using
the varation of fre enery or marginal
fre Energy
Formula so as we can see from the
previous slides uh we do need somehow U
to somehow plan the actions to interact
with the world so if we're trying to
minim minimize or surprise um with the
current observations um so in the action
planning we aim to take actions that
minimize the similar free free energy
term in the future um this is often
called that's the expected free energy
by the way um so in here uh we introduce
some new terms right Theta um is the
model parameters um the reason why this
is here is because we want to also
compute the um
uh modal the surprise over the modal
parameters or the uncertainty of the
modal parameters um so you can see that
the expected fre energy in the future
it's kind of similar to the version of
fre Energy Formula it's only needs um
another model of parameters
parameters and the given the pi or the
actual plant's policy or plant actions
so after a lot of derivations right I'm
we're not getting into like the real
devation here but um here's the end
results that's um something something
minus um minus the weighted means of the
uh L P of OT right so I'll just focus on
this um term is because this is the um
goal of the talk today so basically um
this term lock of p is the expected free
energy derivations on of the instrum uh
instrument mental term so basically uh
this also means that we are trying to
maximize the now we're trying to take
the action that maximize um the future
observations that matches our um prior
parap distributions or what we want
right so normally um to learn to take
actions based um uh to learn to take
actions um to align with what we want to
see in the future um we of needs to
craft and provide the priate preference
manually in advance um and then we T the
option based um we take the options um
that's maximize the likelihoods um given
that
distributions um but this is often not
really practical in the realistic World
um H because we cannot like craft the
manual distributions like every single
time we encounter new environments or
encounter a new task right so what we
can also do is we can also provide a
goal Stat or goal observations directly
to the agents which is more practical um
but in the end the prior preference
distribution is very sparse um and this
provides little to no learning signal to
the
agent as you can see on the figure on
the right and the left right so left is
a primior preference distributions and
right is a single goal distri go State
distributions or goal State
image so uh what can you do to
dynamically uh produce um the uh uh
prior preference right we can try to
learn a prior preference model right
that um produce a goal image at each
time
step so here is on top is the prior
preference model that predictions right
and uh in the bottom here is the model
prediction of the future um given the
sequence of planned actions so we are
trying to say that we um we want to take
the actions um that have uh the roll out
in the Futures predictions matching the
prior preference uh roll out in the
future so how do we do that we first
have to learn the model first
right so in learning uh we can try and
say that each time we achieve a goal
then then we Mark the whole trajectory
as the prior preference trajectory or
the um positive um trajectory or expert
trajectory and then for each
observations marks as go we use a deep
learning like another deep learning
model to estimate start observations um
for example right and then um in
inference time um we actually train when
we train the policy planner uh to
propose the actions right we make the
policy planner proposing the actions
first and then predicts the future
observation based off of that um actions
U that is planned by the policy planner
and then um we actually learn the policy
planner based on the signal that is
emitted from how aligns the predicted
future observation would be um to the
predicted goal
um the predict the predicted goal here
is the actual prary props model outputs
right
um then we train the policy planner with
the um mean Square Arrow or um some kind
of objectives um that's uh predicts uh
uh some kind of objectives between the
predicted goal image and the predicted
future
observation so there's this problem uh
where uh uh it exists between all these
learning schemes because it is very
computational expensive um so it is
generally uh expensive because we have
to work directly with the images so for
example in learning we have to use a
decoder of the um of the PRI prefence
model um to actually predict the goal
image at each time step right um in
inference uh time is also
computationally expensive is because um
it has to learn from the images itself
and computed down from uh the um the
back propagations will have to flow
through the decoder back to the action
planner so here it comes to the actual
methodologies uh we actually use Dynamic
PR preference learning um in the state
space um instead of the observation
space
right so first of all I want to talk a
little bit about the world model so uh
this uh model architecture is um
basically what I have just um drawn in
the background sections but this looks
with robots images so in here we have
the observations um Ot Ot and here's
also the observation the same
observations OT minus one OT um and we
text in the encoder and is the encoder
posterior texting the encoder and we
have the transation prior um and then we
have the decoder right encoder encodes
the image in have the states and then
decode the um the image the state back
to the image and then computes the
accuracy loss right accuracy loss uh is
minus L prop of the P given S as we have
discussed in the variation of pre energy
sections and then the complexity is the
k k Divergence term between the
posterior and the prior right so how do
we compute the prior we compute from um
the previous steps uh States and then we
use the transation model um to estimate
the next States prior right so that's um
that's how we can get the um
prior so uh current work um and popular
Works uh regarding the world model or
generative models um often inrs um the
model called um RSS langage stands for
um recurrent State space model um in the
translation uh model so it's to zoom out
a little bit um we are trying to uh
integrate some kind of temporal
informations Through Time right um so
that's the state of the environment or
the states that we're trying to predict
be more accurate um and it carries more
informations with time um so for example
um we cannot um encod the uh enough
informations from just a single image
because for example um there can be like
uh position and velocity right the
velocity is acquired um through multiple
images um and cannot be
acquired from a single image if does Mak
sense so what we of to do is we try to
integrate a recurrent NE networks that
text in the previous States um or the
previous recurrent States H my T minus
one um and then we also text in the um
encoded
observations um and then with in
transition um we produce the recurrent
neur network will produce the current
recurrent States um and also predicts
the outputs to to put into the uh
transition model um and also it's the
recurrent stat will also uh be served as
inputs to the posterior Network um so
that's basically uh the
idea and then uh the other way uh around
we could just uh do uh the model as
normal so uh in active inflence asan
texting the actions um that's it belief
uh that would lead to its preferred
outcome uh using instrumental signal um
to construct this prior preference um
Pas has um for example provide a go
statement observations directly to the
agents for example mazaka in 2021 with
contrastive active INF um we can also
manually craft a PR prence distributions
um we can also dynamically produces the
preferred observation that each time set
um but as I mentioned already um all
these method is one way or or another
very expensive um or it's very not
practical or in the reward applications
or um it is very computationally
expensive for dynamically producing the
actual observations um for the the
goals so we can also use Behavior
cloning but it's its trajectory diverges
from on the trading trajectory due to um
small mistakes made by agent as well as
environmental um
stochasticity um and also it is because
of ident IND independent and identically
distributed assumptions of positive
exper data distribution so we can um we
we try we will kind of point it because
it's it's not going to um be uh the same
right the two distributions of the
actual um actual trajectories in the
environment will not be the same as um
every single positive trajectory of the
expert
data so to tackle this we try to
leverage a small quantity of seat
imitation data to learn an uh a neur
network that's dynamically produced
preference Over States not observation
but State um at each time step so this
effectively um produces and easily
generated dense instrumental go signal
um and we also design the agent such as
that it moves according to the
trajectory that is is shaped toward its
own estimation of the future States or
future preferred States so it's trying
to notch the its own trajectory on
toward watchs the imitation positive
data distribution so as you can see on
the figure on the left um so you can see
that in Behavior cloning it's trying uh
the actual trajectory is diverges away
from um the actual imitation data where
the prior preference over the states
trying to um get uh trying to be shied
toward the imitation data itself using
the model
signal and ra is our agent um is called
robust active inance um and it learns um
from both epistemic signal and
instrumental signals but in here we'll
just focus on the instrumental signals
and how to construct
it
so uh yeah so basically we use the
decoder um or the likelihood functions
of the generative model to only
visualize on the preferred
observations um not that in training or
test time we do not use the motor
learning uh we do not use the actual
observation uh goal observations by
itself we only use the hidden States so
the goal here is to um get the states
the goal States at each time step be
predicted by the prior preference model
right um You can see that's uh on the
top here is the real trajectory and the
bottom here is the actual um dream
that's the dream of the robots that it
wants to be right um and then we have
predicting that dream
right so here is the actual model of the
Contra recur and state prior preference
learning um uh so basically it has
um it has also similar architecture to
the rssm to the world model um it also
has have an encoder um here it also have
the
translation um but it does not have the
decoder um so how do we actually uh
learn this
uh um prior preference model so first of
all uh we uh learn the world generative
World model as normal right um but when
we say whenever um it's uh whenever the
trajectory is uh positive or a
successful trajectory um we try to
contract um the state of the uh crispy I
just call it crispy um we try to contuct
the state of crispy to the um world
model States and then um whenever the um
trajectory is negative we try to push
away the states um from each other so
that the crispy model um can only
predict the um positive States so how do
we determin um if it is a POS trajectory
um or the negative trajectory without
having a very sparse signal so we will
have a thing called braw or the prior
preference signal so how do we compute
this raw
signal so imagine um this is the real
trajectory um and it is a successful
trajectory for example right so we're
trying to compute um the prior
preference states by
having the rate of the successful States
is at one and it starts from one and it
it be case backward so the case um very
fast and um if so in this like really
far away States from here um they do not
have um enough signal because there's no
goal
um like there's no direct go from that
states
and then there's real trajectory that is
failed right um You can see that the
mountain car cannot reach um the fls on
the right here so whenever it's built um
we can just PL plat the very very last
observation as minus one and then we
start to De Decay backward
negatively
um and then uh we have the prior
preference rate
signal as um very
negative so the reason why it is it has
to be last is because um we want to um
we want to blame the L observations um
hardest so um in order to uh in order
for the agents to just push away from
the failing States very very very strong
um in the very last stage
so in the real trajectory that have like
multiple successes um we try to put all
the one in all the successful States and
then just Decay
backward um as similar to how we Decay
backward in a single success
case so with that s we now uh know how
to comput um the RO and then this will
serve as the dynamic signal um to the
contrasted loss and it creates a dynamic
behavior of the contrasted loss um
that's trying to either push away or um
contract um the two states of the
preseed state and the world model
States so for example in here um there's
if there's positive row um the
contracted block would be um Contra
Contracting all the states together and
maximizing the similarity between the
precipitate states and the world model
States and then we also learn to
minimize the K diversions between the um
complex uh uh the posterior and the
prior uh of over the states of the
crispy
model um this is because we want to
estimate the translations right so we
translation to the um next goal State
and then this goal state has to match
the actual goal um that is the current
stage of the envir of the rssm model or
the world model
um
so in contrast right if row is negative
then we're trying to push away um all
these states away right so we're trying
to maximize this um distance or
minimizing the similarity between the um
world model States and the cryst spe
State and in here notes that there's no
complexity objective is because we don't
want to um predict the next goal that is
um the failing State that's basically
the the
idea so that arrives at the uh general
formula for the objectives of the
contrast State PR preference model um
basically uh it is just masking out um
The Sign of the row and then multiply
with the the K Divergence or the
complexity uh between the posterior and
the prior of the crisby model um and
then we uh minus the row and SE of um
the actual predicted State and the world
model state so same here can be very
much um uh any kind of similarity
functions for example um cosine
similarity um
and then in the in our work we actually
use the actual coine
simar
so in train time we have we have just
talked about training time right so we
have successfully assuming that we have
successfully um learned the prisp model
that predicts the future goal um and in
inference time we've used this um crispy
transation model to estimate future
rollout trajectory of the go right so we
can see that um on the top here is the
observation um actual observations and
in the second row is the actual prior
preference roll outs or predictions of
the future goal uh given the um given
the current
observation so given the uh PL actions
we also training the plant uh the plant
actions right so the actor trying to
predict actions given um the
observations the predicted observation
in the future um so we're trying to say
uh this is uh we're trying to compare uh
the actual PRI prior preference roll
outs with the actual predictions given
the actions
um and then we are trying to uh learn
the action planner based on the signals
or how diver um the future goal is to
our future predictions of the world
given the
options so uh there can be so many um
there can be so many reinforcement
learning agents and active in agents
that can utilize this technique um of
Prior preference learning so active INF
agents um I put my works here um it's ra
and then there's also Chris bakley's
work and baren M work about deep active
influence in varal um policy gradients
methods um and also Auto uh work is is
the scaling of the uh act active
inflence in PDP and not in car
environments and so on right so
reinforcement learning agents there's
all these sorts of um after critics
algorithms like dreamer series um soft
after critic dreaming um ddpg tqc um nd3
and so on so there's a lot of agents
that can utilize the framework because
there's no change um in the original
architecture there's just an add-on um
to how um to how an agents would apply
the private preference learning signal
um into the
system so is the actual flow chart of um
of the agents basically um we start the
agents and for each episodes we evaluat
um the environments um using the world
model and the policy planner um actually
basically we uh uh evaluat in the
environment we let the robots play we
let the robots do the task and then we
collect the uh data and add them to the
replay buffer for example right and then
we can get the main training agent um
logic um and then first of all we sample
the training data from the buffer so in
here we trying to have um we also have
to use um The self-imitation Learning
buffer um
so uh yeah so self-limitation learning
is very good technique um normally to
balance the number of um successful and
failing
trajectories and we also learned um so
first of all we learned the world model
encoder decoder transation on rssm and
then we uh train the epistemics model
but in this case we don't need to care
about it um and then next is the um
Contra Rec St PR preference model um
from the data and then um next we
imagine the future trajectory using the
world model and the policy planner right
we try to estimate the future options um
to be um what is the optimized future
actions for example which we estimates
the future action based on how uh
current state
is and then the world model will be
continuing to bouts in the Futures and
then we dream of the futures
and next is the part that we actually um
infer on the uh crispy model we use a
crispy model to imagine the future
prefence
trajectory um given the goal um given
the current observations and we predict
the future goals roll out goals right
so after that we learn the policy
planner right using the instrumental
signal the instrumental signals here is
computed from the um difference um
between the future goal and the um
predicted future dream of the
world right and then with that the
policy planner can learn from uh from
the uh instrumental
signal so here's our um preliminary
results on um active inflence agent so
basically um we can see um the two top
rows is the mountain and car
environments and the two bottom row is
Rob robotics met a world um push button
environment so let's look at the first
row for example the observation here is
a mountain paru have reached the goal
and for each um observation here we uh
we predict a preference roll out or
preference um or a goal State at that
single time step so in here we can see
that um if the car has not have the
moment yet um then we have to build the
momentum by predicting the car going to
the left for example right and then
after it has built some kind of momentum
we trying uh the actual prior preference
model predicting the car would go to the
right go forward right when it goes here
and the prence model will predict the
car to be um going closer to the goal
something like this so the same applies
to the um robot environments where the
actual observation is the third uh row
and the uh prior preference roll out is
on the fourth row so we can see that uh
it is also trying to estimates the dream
or the dream of the goal of the robots
is to actually push the
button so um there's different kind of
experiment setup that we are trying to
learn um basically we have uh four
trials on each environment and then we
train the experts um using as sof critic
or po proximal policy
optimization um to collect um a small
amount of seed data normally is about uh
20 episodes something um 20 to to 30
episodes um so we test mostly on three
mains environments or suits um first of
all is Mountain car there's only one
task um metal W is 13 task so here's um
all red robots here's metal war and then
the robot suit we have two task and then
um the C regarding camera setups uh we
use um three views for met world and
four views for um the robo
suit so the green check mark here
denotes uh that the robots has uh
successfully solve the
task um here's a robo suit door open
door and then um here's Robo suit lift
where it can successfully lift the
block and here's more U solving agent
tasks so basically agent with Crispy
exhibits and ability to perform
successfully early on um and uh so agent
with without crispy uh struggle to
actually succeed on solving the
environment um and we also test on
another other environment as well for
example gasum robotics or and risk task
um you can you can see in the middle
image on over
here so actually you go to the
discussion sections so actually um I
want to make a note that um with respect
to the crispy subm model um RM model
utilize contrastive objectives to adapt
its parameters so basically it solely
learns on um estimating the world model
in coted States while pushing itself
away from undesired World model States
or trajectory so this does not require
or the learning of the of the decoder so
we we only make sure of the Learned
decoder in the generative World model um
to visualize
the uh to visualize the preferred
observations um from the estimated
crispy States so experimentally we
remark that this is an um that's we only
use um this decoder um to as an
auxiliary tools um to prove um that the
states of the contusive recurrence Prime
preference model uh is useful
so theoretically Behavior cloting will
be unable to achieve a great uh success
in multile multi goal environments due
to its Reliance on a fix and finite size
uh imitation sample pool um the expert
trajectory in this fixed pool May
further differ from the actual
trajectories um that the agent needs to
take to solve the problem at hand um for
example there's a distributional gap in
in observation
and there and um it requires different
sets of actions to be taken for example
right um
so on the other hand right crispy learns
to produce dynamically um the goal
sticks and not the go observation right
um so we can empirically confirm in
simulation that our agent um with
Dynamic prior preference learning does
not suffer from the goal miss much
problem uh in the training
phase so this is very applicable
applicable to the multi-goal
environments
so um we can see that um this P
preference learning uh techniques has a
lot of practical applications in
different robotic tasks um with for
example those with potential dangers in
the operations um and functioning for
example when human safety must be
considered right um for example a um
trying to drive a autonomous driving car
system where uh it has to have or it has
to predict um the future um goal right
the future goal is not to hit the human
for example right um and we can also
make a lot of advancement in imitation
learning in research community and it
can be um applied by the wide range of
um reinforcement learning in active
inference
agents um and then the last one is to
scale the the active inference agents on
um the real world robotics
agent so future work words actually
considered um importing or integrating
the dynamic PR preference learning in
latent State space model um for example
varation of Dynamics discret variable
Auto encoders or tension waiting models
um and also uh there's another models uh
physical neur robotic system um which
entails an embodied and active and
survival oriented formulations of active
perception and World model
learning so in this uh talk um uh we
have discussed a lot of ideas about
being able to estimate the particular
goal or preferred State um at any
particular time step is very useful um
for cognitive control agents so as our
results demonstrates the agent can then
learn to adapt the tech actions that
leads to um a estimated goal um and then
um in contrast to the approach is taken
in the imentation learning and behavior
cloning literature um which train the
agent's policy based solely based on the
fixed collected expert data sets in our
framework the expert signal is estimated
dynamically um through an Adaptive prior
preference model right closing this Gap
the domain gap between the actual
trajectories and the collected trading
imitation trajectory or preferred
trajectory um and then we also discussed
the gener generative model um and and
coder decod transations and how the
varation of free energy work and then
how to learn the model and then we
finally we discussed the contrasted
recurrent State prior preference model
um with a self-revision mechanism and
then discuss the model learning and then
inference um object deted um and how to
integrate stat into the agent planner
learning system and then we show the
results for um the robotic task and then
I mention how it can be applied to
different
fields so that concludes my presentation
um and thank you very much for um
listening thank you that was amazing
really great job with the background
math done only like a PhD student can
but it was great to see how you brought
it all together and connected your
research to it all at the end so thank
you that's all for now see you later
thank you see
you
e e